<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Animadversions on Capt. Wilkinson's information being highly conducive to the better informing and disabusing the minds of men and tending to the publick peace and safety.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1682</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 67 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 11 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A25441</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A3193</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R15953</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11926571</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11926571</idno>
            <idno type="VID">51046</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A25441)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 51046)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 48:8)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Animadversions on Capt. Wilkinson's information being highly conducive to the better informing and disabusing the minds of men and tending to the publick peace and safety.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>18 [i.e 20] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Walter Davis,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1682.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Yale University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Wilkinson, Henry, 17th cent.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Restoration, 1660-1688.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:51046:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:51046:1"/>
            <p>ANIMADVERSIONS ON Capt. Wilkinſon's INFORMATION. Being highly conducive to the better informing and diſabuſing the Minds of Men, and tending to the publick Peace and Safety.</p>
            <q>He that is firſt in his own Cauſe ſeems juſt, but his neighbour comes and ſearches him out,
<bibl>
                  <hi>Prov. 18.17.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Walter Davis,</hi> 1682.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:51046:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:51046:2"/>
            <head>ANIMADVERSIONS ON Capt. Wilkinſon's INFORMATION.</head>
            <p>SINCE I ſaw this Information, I have been big with Expectation of ſome notable Skirmiſhes with it. But finding none ſo hardy, as to incounter the Captain, I have adventured to enter the Liſts, and take up the Gantlet againſt him.</p>
            <p>To the Reader, p. 1. he gives ſome account of his adventures and ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings.</p>
            <p n="1">1. His Adventures, he had <hi>ſerved his late Majeſty of bleſſed Memory, and his most glorious Majeſty King</hi> Charles <hi>the Second;</hi> and that particularly in being <hi>inſtrumental in his Reſtauration:</hi> And</p>
            <p n="2">2. His Sufferings, for <hi>(with many others in the ſame Service)</hi> he had the <hi>misfortune to be much impoveriſhed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Where we will obſerve that the Captain pleads Poverty, and makes the cauſe of it to be His Majeſties Service. And yet in the very ſame Page, Parag. 3. he owns that ſince His Majeſties Return, he hath been a great Projector, and for the moſt part loſt by his Projects: And hath likewiſe ſpent <hi>above one thouſand pounds in aſſiſting one Mr.</hi> Caſtillian Morris.</p>
            <p>Now if the Captain's Eſtate had ever been conſiderable, I doubt not but we ſhould have had an account of it, that we might withall have ſeen the <hi>greatneſs of his Sufferings.</hi> But whatever that was, his Poverty could not be great, ſince he could afford, ever ſince His Majeſties Reſtauration, to be a continual loſer by Projects of his own, and ſpend above a thouſand pounds upon his Friend; and after all, be in a capacity of leaving his Country <hi>honourably,</hi> p. 9. As for the Debts that make him a Priſoner, they were contracted by his keeping a Ship, his Family, and above thirty Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants idle on the River from <hi>April</hi> till <hi>Auguſt,</hi> together with his ingage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments for other men, and Actions brought upon him by Paſſengers, who ſeveral of them Arreſted him for damages in being ſo long delayed, and together threw him into the <hi>Counter in Woodstreet,</hi> to whom notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding all, he was ſtill capable of offering <hi>fair and reaſonable ſatisfaction;</hi> which being not accepted, he removed himſelf to the Priſon of the <hi>Kings-Bench, Sept.</hi> 17. Page 3. to the end.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:51046:3"/>
            <p>How then was the Captain impoveriſhed by His Majeſties Service? A loſer he might be, impoveriſhed he was not: It is an eaſe to ſome men to nick their private loſſes on the publick ſcore. Hereby they hope at leaſt to wipe off from themſelves all reproach of extravagancy, and ill man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>agement of their affairs. And men of more deſigning heads, as the Captain ſeems to be, think by ſuch little Arts, to fix themſelves the faſter in popular eſteem, who reckon that hope and revenge equally conſpire to make them true to that intereſt they have now eſpouſed; and therefore do not fear their return to their Maſter, who, they tell them, has cut off, not like <hi>Darius,</hi> their Lips, Noſe and Ears; but their Houſes, Lands, and Credit in the World.</p>
            <p>But in caſe this had been true, which yet himſelf evidently overthrows, what need was there of that Parentheſis, <hi>viz. (with many others in the ſame Service?)</hi> unleſs to upbraid the King with ingratitude; or to hint, that miſeries are the uſual attendants on that Service; and by both to af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fright others from their duties in the like nature. Surely Soldiers might be content to loſe their Arrears, when all honeſt Subjects were hurl'd into a common ruine, while the King himſelf did loſe, one his Life? The other his Crowns? The Parliament Army might have fared as bad, had not the Commons, whoſe they were, paid them by <hi>Theft</hi> and <hi>Sacriledge.</hi> Whereas had the King overcame, themſelves had been the loſers, while His Majeſties Forces had been well, and more honeſtly paid too. But yet to the Reader, Page 1. he grants that it was <hi>impoſſible for His Majeſty to gratifie all that wanted his Royal bounty.</hi> Therefore as his own Poverty is falſly placed on the account of his Service; ſo the Poverty of others in the ſame Service is mentioned, either to no purpoſe, or to an ill end.</p>
            <p>In the Information, Page 2. 3. he acknowledges he had formerly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired to <hi>Farm</hi> ſomething of <hi>His Majesties Revenues,</hi> which, it ſeems, he could not attain to, and doubtleſs for that reaſon was <hi>reſolved not to come at the Court,</hi> as he once and again declares, <hi>Nor would trust any Courtier he knew for a Groat,</hi> p. 3. And leſt he ſhould not ſufficiently ſpit his venom, he beſpatters the whole Pamphlet with expreſſions of an ill nature that way, as Page 4. that he would <hi>not trust the Promiſes of Courtiers.</hi> And Page 8. that he could <hi>freely draw his Sword againſt them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>From which things together we may ſee the Man's Complexion, <hi>viz.</hi> that he was an Old Cavalier, but having by fond Projects waſted his Eſtate, and miſſed expected rewards, he is now grown ſullen, hath eſpouſed ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther intereſt, and in a pet removes from <hi>York-ſhire</hi> to <hi>London,</hi> and here falls in with the concerns of <hi>Carolina.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now all this while the Captain hath been induſtriouſly laying a two<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold deſign, As</p>
            <p n="1">1. To build a little Porch to the Fabrick of his following Diſcourſe, and by the ſpecious pretexts of Loyalty, and the boaſts of former Services, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cariouſly to introduce a belief of the matter of his Information: And</p>
            <p n="2">2. To ſatisfie the People that he is totally fallen off from the <hi>Court-Party,</hi> as ſome love to ſpeak, and which, in vulgar acceptation, is the King, Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of State, and <hi>their Adherents, viz.</hi> thoſe who faithfully retain the Principles of Honeſty and Allegiance.</p>
            <p>Under which ſhade the People do herd and hug themſelves in the thoughts of a Proſelyte, who forſooth muſt be believed in all he is pleaſed
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:51046:3"/>to ſay; though for no other Reaſon, but becauſe he was once a loyal Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, or an honeſt man.</p>
            <p>But a man's former Loyalty and Service, if once he becomes a Male-con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, cannot in reaſon be allowed to derive Reputation to his preſent Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>contents, but muſt rather be judged an occaſion of heightning the ſame, and of hurrying him the faſter into deſperate Reſolves: Becauſe when high thoughts of former Merits, and the ſenſe of preſent Neglects, have drawn a man off to another Party, he there is carried on not only by Intereſt, as before, but alſo by the acceſſion of Revenge. Thus when Pride, Covetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and deſperate Fortunes, had made Hereticks in the Church, and evil Members in the State, they were ever obſerved to have been worſer Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, than thoſe who were born and bred amongſt the Hetorodox in Faith and Loyalty: Of which, perhaps our own Times may afford ſome In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances.</p>
            <p>And truly this ſeems to be the Captain's Caſe, as may be conjectured from ſeveral parts of his Papers, and particularly from <hi>pag.</hi> 8. where he ſaith, that he told the King—<hi>he knew his duty to his Majesty, and would not draw a Sword against him,</hi> (a great Favour indeed) <hi>but could freely do it against ſome of the Court</hi>—which is juſt the language of thoſe very men, whom the Captain glories he had ſerved the King againſt in the late Civil War: For that Rebellion pretended only the Honour and Safety of the King, and to take away evil Counſellors from before him, that his Throne might be eſtabliſhed. And is the Captain indeed reconcil'd to theſe Pleas? Is it now uncharitable to ſuſpect him a Friend to a <hi>true Protestant Aſſociati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> which pretends the Safety of the King, and that in a way of levying War againſt him? It is moſt apparent, that thoſe men who might fall by the Captain's Hand, died innocently, whoſe blood therefore himſelf muſt anſwer for; or elſe that himſelf is travelling the Road to the ſame Deſerts. Or ſuppoſe he never proceed any farther than words, yet what man of any Face or Conſcience, of any Love and Tenderneſs to his King, Countrey, and Religion, can make uſe of thoſe very Pleas, that have led to ſo many Murthers, to ſuch Devaſtations and Ruines, as by ſuch means have fallen upon this Church and Nation? But it ſeems he is become a new man, by having entered upon the old way of Sin.</p>
            <p>He faſtens his Charge at Court particularly upon my Lord <hi>Hallifax,</hi> and my Lord <hi>Hyde,</hi> and afterwards on my <hi>Lord Chancellor;</hi> Perſonages juſtly admired both for their Performances, and ſteady Loyalty: In which he jumps exactly with the moſt open and bare-faced Enemies of our Peace and Government. And indeed the ſad Memorials of the late Earl of <hi>Strafford</hi> and Archbiſhop <hi>Land,</hi> do remind us, that thoſe who would pull down the Crown, begin at the beſt Supporters of it. Indeed he excuſes the King <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form. pag.</hi> 3. ſaying, He is <hi>aſſured</hi> his Majeſty did not put them on the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours to corrupt him: And <hi>pag.</hi> 7. <hi>If I had been exhorted by the best Divine in</hi> England, <hi>he could not have ſaid more than his Majesty.</hi> But yet he wounds him in his Miniſters of State; which is the old way of wounding the King in and through them. This is the method of that moſt daring Anſwer to his Majeſties moſt gracious Declaration, the two parts of the <hi>No Protestant Plot,</hi> which it ſelf hath a Plot in it, <hi>viz.</hi> to proſtitute all Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority and preſent Eſtabliſhments to vulgar Rapes and Violence, and of moſt other Libels expoſed to ſale. And indeed it may well be of ancient
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:51046:4"/>and modern Practice; for we find a plain Example for it in Scripture, which the <hi>good People,</hi> as the <hi>Aſſociation</hi> calls them, chooſe to follow rather than Precept; for <hi>Judas</hi> betrays while he cryes <hi>Maſter,</hi> and <hi>kiſſes</hi> him.</p>
            <p>Now the thing he ſeems to reflect on my Lord of <hi>Hallifax,</hi> and my Lord <hi>Hyde,</hi> is of a very high Nature, <hi>viz.</hi> a deſign of making him an Evidence againſt the Lord <hi>Shaftsbury:</hi> For <hi>pag.</hi> 4. <hi>They,</hi> viz. <hi>Booth</hi> and <hi>Bains, told me, I might be aſſured of what I would deſire from my Lord</hi> Hallifax, <hi>and my Lord</hi> Hyde. And a few lines after, <hi>Mr.</hi> Booth <hi>told me,—I was intended</hi> 500 l. <hi>per an. or</hi> 10000 l. <hi>in Money.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Though all wiſe and obſerving men well know, that their Lordſhips want no Pen to vindicate their Truth and Honour, which, like the Moon, keeps her courſe, and wonted brightneſs, though here ſorry Curs may be bawling at her. For could any Imputation have been faſtned upon them, it is well known that wiſer Heads than the Captain's would not long ſince have done it; when it was the joy of good men, that his Majeſty had ſuch Miniſters, whom ſome would have had removed, but could give no Reaſon for it: Whence we conjectured, that the Cauſes of their Offence was indeed theſe Perſonages Commendation. Yet however we ſhall conſider ſome few things in and appertaining to this Matter. As,</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Captain doth not pretend, that they ever ſaid they came with theſe Propoſals by their Lordſhips Order or Knowledge; nay himſelf makes ſo blind a buſineſs of it, that <hi>pag.</hi> 3. <hi>parag.</hi> 2. he ſaith, <hi>By whom</hi> Mr. <hi>Booth</hi> was put upon this method, <hi>God knows;</hi> he is <hi>aſſured it was not his Majesty,</hi> but on whom to fix it, he cannot tell: Here then is a <hi>Scanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum Magnatum,</hi> without any pretext of Reaſon. Suppoſe they had uſed theſe Names and Authorities, but yet ſo, that the Captain could gain no certain knowledge from thence, even Chriſtian Charity would have obliged him, had they been his Equals, not to have mentioned the Perſons, had it been needful to have declared the thing. Therefore this raſh Procedure ſpeaks it a clear deſign in him to ſerve the popular Humour and Intereſt, and to help the driving on that Deſign againſt King and Kingdom, which hath hitherto found theſe Perſonages ſuch Rubs in its way.</p>
            <p>I will here premiſe ſome few things: As,</p>
            <p n="1">1. That they might know the Captain privy to ſome Deſigns, as Mr. <hi>Booth</hi> hath ſworn. Or,</p>
            <p n="2">2. That they might at leaſt conjecture, that if there were any Deſigns from diſſenting Parties, that in all reaſon they were not wholly hid from the Captain; which Preſumption we ſhall ſhew ſufficient Reaſon for anon. And,</p>
            <p n="3">3. That they knew the Captain to be poor and covetous, and reſolved to make his beſt Markets of what he knew. From which things we argue thus: Suppoſe (becauſe Suppoſitions grant nothing) that this <hi>Booth</hi> and <hi>Bains</hi> might, unknown to theſe Lords, uſe their Lordſhips Names in ſuch ſort only, as to let the Captain underſtand, that he need not queſtion but that his Services would be conſidered, that his own Pardon and Rewards would be certain. I can ſee no evil in all this, nor can any cenſure it, but they muſt withal condemn the Proceedings and Methods uſed toward <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pists,</hi> in order to ſome diſcovery there. They were promiſed Pardons; and what greater gift there can be to a man than his Life, I do not know. They had a proſpect of Gain from their Narratives; of Guards and Penti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:51046:4"/>which the ſuſpitious and reſtleſs minds of Diſſenters made neceſſary; and even the Houſe of Commons moved His Majeſty about Dr. <hi>Oats</hi> his Allowance, even while there were Perſons to be Tryed, whom the ſame <hi>Oats</hi> was kept an Evidence againſt. Which things were as apt in their own natures to ſway, and corrupt the mind, as the Arts, if true, which the Captain here complains of. Of which nature we ſhall touch on ſome other things as they lye in our way, whereby we ſhall diſcover the une<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qual minds of Diſſenters, who will not endure the ſame methods in one matter, which they applaud in another, though the matters are both of the ſame nature; therefore I cannot imagine what other reaſon can be aſſigned, but their own Intereſt and Preſervation.</p>
            <p>But I ſhall at preſent make out that it cannot in any reaſon be believed, that there were any ſuch offers as theſe really made: For,</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Captain did offer Page 4. for <hi>two thouſand Guineys</hi> to make a Diſcovery: Therefore would never have ſtood out, had there been offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed five hundred pounds <hi>per annum,</hi> or ten thouſand pounds in Money for the ſame Service; eſpecially if to this there had been added, as he ſpeaks Page 5. five hundred pounds <hi>per annum</hi> more out of an Eſtate in <hi>Ireland.</hi> But you will object that the Captain offered this as a wheedle to diſcover the bottom of the deſign. Therefore we proceed,</p>
            <p n="2">2. There could be no ſuch deſign in it, becauſe the Libel it ſelf doth ſhew, that his Work and Rewards were both made known at the firſt offer, before he propoſed any terms himſelf. But you will find a moſt palpable and vile incongruity in this very particular; for Page 2. Parag. 3. he ſaith, that on <hi>Tueſday Octob.</hi> 11. 1681. Mr. <hi>Booth</hi> told him, he might <hi>have five hundred pounds</hi> per annum <hi>ſettled upon himſelf and Heirs, or ten thouſand pounds in Money</hi> for the Service. And yet Page 3, 4. he tells you that on <hi>Wedneſday Octob.</hi> 12. 1681. himſelf did offer for two thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Guineys to diſcover. Now let any man in reaſon judge, whether it is in the leaſt probable, that if he might have had the greater ſum for do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this thing on the <hi>Tueſday,</hi> that he would offer, though in deſign only to do it for the leſſer ſum on <hi>Wedneſday:</hi> This is a ſtrange way of bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaining, and takes away all Faith and Credit of the Relation. He tells us Page 3. that his Friend kept a dayly account of all that paſſed in this affair, and here he puts not only in Figures the day of the Month, but at large the day of the Week too, as <hi>Tueſday</hi> and <hi>Wedneſday,</hi> therefore it could not be a miſtake, that might happen in a true relation, but an over-ſight in a wicked Forgery; by ſuch little means it ſometimes pleaſes God to diſcover great Impoſtors.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Notice being given above, that the Captain declared himſelf willing for ſuch a ſum to make a Diſcovery, Mr. <hi>Graham</hi> is ſent to him to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand whether he had ſaid any ſuch thing, he anſwers yes, and that for ſo much Money in hand he would do it. But when Mr. <hi>Graham</hi> ſaid he had no order from the Lords to make a bargain, nor would any ſuch thing be done, by reaſon a promiſe would deſtroy his Evidence, the Captain preſſes ſo earneſtly after the Money, that he cunningly finds an evaſion, pleading that it ſhould be given, not for the ſake of his Diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very, but towards his former loſſes. But finding no Money would come that way, and perhaps finding better incouragements another, he falls back, and will ſay not a word. Theſe things Mr. <hi>Graham</hi> a Gentleman
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:51046:5"/>of <hi>Cliffords-Inn,</hi> and a Perſon of a good Fortune and unſpotted Reputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, is ready to depoſe upon Oath, when lawfully called; but there is ſo little need of that, that the thing appears plain from divers of the Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain's own expreſſions, as Page 4. he requires two thouſand Guineys <hi>to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards his loſſes,</hi> which is his very Plea to Mr. <hi>Graham, and then,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>I will diſcover.</hi> And in the fifth Line after—I told him, <hi>When I had that Money and a general Pardon, I would then do any Service I could.</hi> He re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolves to have the Money, and will not depend on kindneſs, the want of which was the reaſon of his ſilence, and afterwards denial. The ſame Mr. <hi>Graham</hi> doth declare, that he is verily perſwaded, had he made a bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, the Captain would have diſcovered a Plot, if any he knew of, or made one, if none.</p>
            <p n="4">4. If any had had ſuch a deſign upon the Captain, it is not in reaſon to be thought, that they would imploy Mr. <hi>Graham,</hi> a man of undoubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Reputation, as any inquirer will find him to be, until the good people ſhall pleaſe to make him Beaſt and Devil, as they do all that oppoſe them. Becauſe ſuch a perſon is no fit inſtrument in ſuch a work, nor any way ſuit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to <hi>Booth</hi> and <hi>Bains,</hi> if they were ſuch as the Captain repreſents them.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Could it be ſuppoſed that any had ſuch a deſign on the Captain and the Lord <hi>Sh</hi> — yet it cannot in reaſon be imagined that they would, after ſo many repulſes, follow him with ſo frequent and importunate ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſes as he there relates: And after all, force him by a Warrant to an Examination, that being the moſt improbable way of corrupting an old ſullen Soldier, and the readieſt courſe to give a diſcontented Fellow, that had now embarqued in another bottom, an opportunity of expoſing them to the common Odium of all Mankind: And of reeking his malice, which runs out at every part of his diſcourſe to the utmoſt upon them. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore if we will act by any meaſures of reaſon, we muſt conclude, that in caſe the Captain had not given a very great ſuſpition that he knew ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of theſe matters, he never had been examin'd about it. Therefore let himſelf be guilty of ſuch deſigns or not guilty, privy to them or not, it is not to be queſtioned amongſt reaſonable men, but that the Captain in this affair, hath plaid the Fool and Knave at once, and did cunningly preſs after an opportunity of making his Markets, which he hath done to ſo much advantage, that he is now releaſed from Priſon, walks the Exchange, and takes his Lodgings in the City: And alſo, when the Juſtice of the Council and Government would not do what we may preſume others have, to ſpit his venom to the utmoſt on the Court and Government at once.</p>
            <p>Now let us ſum up theſe things together: That</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Captain is needy, and reſolves to have Money on the one hand or the other.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That he offered for two thouſand Guineys to diſcover a Plot againſt the King and Government.</p>
            <p n="3">3. When he is told the making a bargain will ſpoil his Evidence, he finds out a way to ſalve that Objection, <hi>viz.</hi> the Money ſhall be given towards the loſſes he ſuſtain'd, and not on condition of his Diſcovery.</p>
            <p n="4">4. When all would not do, he turns Cat in Pan, complies with thoſe People he would before have delivered to the Laws, and pretends 10000 <hi>l.</hi> were promiſed him to make ſuch a diſcovery againſt King and Government:
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:51046:5"/>But, as providence will have it, makes the Story utterly incredible, by making the 10000 <hi>l.</hi> to be offered him one day, and himſelf to propoſe the thing on condition of 2000 Guineys the very next day; for it can never be believed, that he ſhould offer to do it for a much leſs Sum, if the very day before he had been urged to do it for a much greater Sum.</p>
            <p n="5">5. That after this Service done to the good People, he is forthwith re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaſed from Priſon, and made a Gentleman.</p>
            <p>And I leave it to any honeſt man to tell me, whether he is not perſwaded in his own Mind and Reaſon, that <hi>ſo much</hi> Confeſſion, <hi>ſo much</hi> utter Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probability in his Stories, <hi>ſo much</hi> Gain and Enlargement upon the Service done, <hi>ſo much</hi> Evidence from Mr. <hi>Graham</hi> and Mr. <hi>Booth,</hi> who againſt <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pists</hi> would be received as the beſt Witneſs in the World, would not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade any true <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Jury, to hang up <hi>Papists</hi> to the number of themſelves.</p>
            <p>There is a ſecond part of a <hi>No Protestant Plot;</hi> ſurely there is ſomething ſticks, where they keep ſuch rubbing: The man, I ſuppoſe, would not have Antichriſtian Names put upon Chriſtian Practices; <hi>Plots</hi> and <hi>Treaſons</hi> are the Works of <hi>Papiſts;</hi> the good People have nothing unleſs <hi>Solemn Leagues</hi> and <hi>Covenants,</hi> and <hi>Aſſociations.</hi> The Creature, <hi>pag.</hi> 9. would per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade the Lord <hi>H.</hi> and the Earl of <hi>H.</hi> to fall upon Mr. <hi>Booth,</hi> for uſing their Lordſhips Names in the matter and manner, as this Informer <hi>Wilkinſon</hi> doth relate, or elſe to lye under the ſuppoſed Guilt of what this Libel taxes them with; the reaſonableneſs of which let any man judge by our Obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions upon it. Doubtleſs there is in this very thing a Plot to bring Ruine upon the King's Evidence; and if they could by ſuch Artifices do it in this Inſtance, we doubt not but that they would ſoon ſend out another Infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation to do the like in another Inſtance; by which means the King ſhould have no Evidence, but what would ſoon have the Penalties of the Aſſocia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion inflicted upon him, that is, he ſhould be purſued <hi>to deſtruction.</hi> The Argument is a two-horn'd thing called a <hi>Dilemma:</hi> They have got, it ſeems, ſuch Creatures amongſt them; and ſeems reſolved to have its end ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther this way or that, <hi>viz.</hi> the King's Evidence muſt be ruined, or the King's Friends blaſted in their Honour, and made as uncapable as may be, of do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Majeſty and the Kingdom ſervice.</p>
            <p>But at length the Cloud is extended, and made to eclipſe his <hi>R. Highneſs,</hi> out of whoſe Eſtate in <hi>Ireland,</hi> the Captain ſaith, he ſhould have had the addition of 500 <hi> l. per an. pag.</hi> 5. What is argued to ſhow the vanity and falſhood of the man in reference to the Lords, is apt to do ſo here, and that with ſome advantage too, becauſe it is ſtill more improbable that he ſhould be offered 1000 <hi> l. per an.</hi> for that which he himſelf by his own confeſſion was earneſt to do for 2000 Guineys. But however if he had miſſed this Point, he had done but little; for <hi>if we do not kill the Heir, the Inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance can't be ours.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But you will ſay, If there was not ſomething of this nature in it, how comes the Captain to be ſo preſſed upon in this Affair? To which I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, The Reaſon might be from his own Offer for ſuch a Sum to make a diſcovery; which Offer himſelf, you ſee, confeſſes. And that this was not done meerly to humour the Matter, as he ſpeaks, but in all likelihood was the firſt Propoſal made, we have argued to be very probable, from the Time and the Sums which the Captain mentions; for it is utterly mad and
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:51046:6"/>irrational to believe, that they ſhould offer him 10000 <hi>l.</hi> for ſuch a Service one day, and that himſelf ſhould offer the ſame Service for 2000 Guineys the next day. Therefore, it may be, himſelf gave the occaſion of all this Stir.</p>
            <p>But moreover, the Lord <hi>Shaftsbury</hi> and others ſtood then accuſed of a Deſign upon the King and Government, from which his Lordſhip is ſince acquit, but it was then in ſuſpence: And in caſe there had been ſuch a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign, it was moſt highly probable that this Captain might be privy to it. For,</p>
            <p n="1">1. The ſaid Captain was often with the E. of <hi>Sh</hi>—as appears from his Information.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The ſaid Captain had from the Earl <hi>always a very kind Reception.</hi> To the Reader, <hi>pag.</hi> 2.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The Captain yields, That he rode with Sword and Piſtols out of Town with the Lord <hi>Sh</hi>—when he went to <hi>Oxford, pag.</hi> 6. which <hi>Ox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford</hi> was the Place where, and this the Time when, this Attempt on the Perſon of the King was ſaid ſhould have been made.</p>
            <p n="4">4. They were both in no great Charity with the Court. And,</p>
            <p n="5">5. The Captain was a Military man, ſunk in the World, and newly come to Town to put himſelf into ſome new way of Life, and therefore a very likely Inſtrument for ſuch an Undertaking, if any ſuch Deſign had been, which was then in queſtion.</p>
            <p>All which things were known: Whence it was moſt reaſonable to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jecture, that if there was ſuch a Deſign, it muſt in all probability be known to this man; upon which Preſumption, it was moſt fit he ſhould be exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned: For it is part of the buſineſs and end of Government, to diſcover evil Members in the Body politick, to ſtop the Gangrene, and preſerve the ſounder parts in their Soundneſs. All which was no more, than what was ordinarily done for the diſcovery of a <hi>Popiſh</hi> Plot; for many were aſper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, impriſoned, examined and tryed for their Lives, upon whom no ſuch Evil could be found.</p>
            <p>All this time theſe People commended this for Vigilance, and a Chriſtian Zeal, and never found fault, till it comes to touch their own Parties. It is therefore Partiality, and not any injuſtice in the thing it ſelf, that makes them complain.</p>
            <p>Well, in this Negotiation, the Captain, we have ſeen, <hi>pag.</hi> 4. offers for 2000 <hi>Guineys to diſcover what he knew,</hi> implying thereby, that he knew ſomething. Which is declared to the Council: Whereupon Mr. <hi>Graham</hi> is ſent to diſcourſe him, to whom the Captain owns that Propoſal, and makes the ſame again to him; but becauſe no Money was coming, as before, his mouth ſhuts in ſilence: Which is very plain from ſome other Expreſſions, not quoted before; as <hi>pag.</hi> 3. I told him, <hi>I would ſay nothing, nor appear at the Court, till I was conſidered for my Sufferings.</hi> Pag. 4. <hi>I told him,</hi> viz. <hi>Mr.</hi> Booth, <hi>When I had that Money, and a general Pardon, I would then do any ſervice I could,—but I would not trust the Promiſes of Courtiers;</hi> but when he ſaw he muſt truſt, he won't traffick. And I am perſwaded theſe things had never been put into his Information, had not the ſame, with ſome Additions, been made known to Mr. <hi>Graham,</hi> whoſe Credit he could not blaſt ſo eaſily as the others.</p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:51046:6"/>
            <p>But the Council will not be ſo put off, but bring him by Warrant to examination, a moſt undoubted Evidence of the integrity, and upright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of their intentions and proceedings; and truly both King and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil might very reaſonably be put by the Captains offer, upon expectation of ſome conſiderable diſcovery he could make; and likewiſe upon his unexpected departure from what he had propoſed, his Examination might well be ſtrict and preſſing; he having by the ſaid offer given juſt cauſe of ſuſpition that there was ſome wickedneſs at bottom, which he was loth to diſcover. Which things, if done for the finding out a Popiſh Intrigue, would have been applauded for Zeal and Integrity, by that very Party that now condemns them for Wickedneſs and Subornation.</p>
            <p>Now if there was no ſuch deſign for alteration of Government, or ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe there was, but the Captain knew not of it, himſelf may be much mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaken in thinking theſe methods, which were uſed to find out a truth, which he was ſuppoſed to be privy to, were really intended to oblige him to the witneſſing a falſhood.</p>
            <p>To ſuppoſe there was ſuch a deſign, and that known to the Captain too, it was very eaſie for him, by offering to diſcover for 2000 Guineys, to draw on Diſcourſes, it may be ſomewhat farther than might be conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient for them to know, who were not acquainted with the whole In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trigue, and all its circumſtances, and yet the perſons tranſacting the affair, ſtill remain free from all evil deſigns: And then to turn all to the palliate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſame Treaſons, and to the farther carrying them on againſt the Government, by charging ſuch evil practices upon it. Which indeed would mightily tickle a revengeful Spirit, which the Captain all along diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covers againſt the Court, by which is vulgarly underſtood, as was before noted, King and Government.</p>
            <p>But now to excuſe his offer of diſcovering, he hath a poor <hi>Salvo,</hi> Page 4. <hi>But I still told them I knew nothing by my Lord</hi> Shaftsbury: Now obſerve the ſubject of their diſcourſe was, whether he knew any ſuch thing by the ſaid Lord? He anſwers, <hi>For</hi> 2000 <hi>Guineys I will diſcover what I know,</hi> which is a plain conceſſion that he knew ſomething; and yet ſaith he at the ſame time, <hi>I told them I knew nothing.</hi> Here is an Oppoſition in the very terms, they are plainly things that cannot poſſibly be reconciled or ſtand together: <hi>He knows;</hi> for <hi>I will diſcover what I know,</hi> and yet <hi>I know nothing.</hi> He will diſcover, and yet hath nothing to diſcover; which is to ſay and unſay, and in plain Engliſh, to demand 2000 Guineys for juſt no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, which is ſuch a monſtrous thing, that no man in his wits can be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve it. This is worſe than buying a Pig in a Poke, for it is ſuppoſed there is a Pig, though not known what an one: but here your Chapman tells you there is a Pig, then in the next words ſaith he, there is no Pig: And yet at the ſame time asks a vaſt rate for the Pig. Certainly ſuch an one would bring himſelf in danger of being either begg'd for a Fool, or taken up for <hi>Bedlam:</hi> And in each inſtance the buyer might go as a fit Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panion with the ſeller, nor is he more wiſe or ſober than either, that can believe ſo fond a Story. But would we put any ſenſe upon this, which hath plainly no ſenſe in it? the beſt we can ſay is, that the Captain doth equivocate and falſifie, in either bringing ſuſpition on the Innocent, or in acquitting the Guilty.</p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:51046:7"/>
            <p>Now becauſe we have before ſhown, that there were many reaſons that might induce a perſwaſion that the Captain might be privy to ſuch a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign, if any ſuch had been; we will now obſerve what anſwer he returns to all thoſe things, and let us ſuppoſe his Innocence, yet the Pleas he makes, do not at all clear, but ſeem rather to derive a much greater ſuſpition upon him. For</p>
            <p n="1">1. He owns the Lord <hi>S</hi>—kindneſs towards him; but ſaith Inform. Page 2. that the reaſon of his Lordſhips reſpects was, <hi>becauſe I had ſerved His Majesty,</hi> Parag. 1.</p>
            <p>To which I ſhall anſwer only this, that he is very happy in his Lordſhips favours, which come to him founded on ſuch a bottom, and I wiſh there were many more ſuch inſtances. But</p>
            <p n="2">2. He pleads Inform. Page 2. Parag. 3. <hi>That none will believe, I ſhould be made privy to ſuch a deſign, (if ſuch a thing was) being I had ſerved His Majesty—</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Which is truly no reaſon at all, unleſs the Captain can prove of Loyalty, as ſome hold of ſaving grace, that it can never be loſt. I pray how many inſtances confuſe him, if we have recourſe back to the laſt Rebellion, in which ſome were in Arms againſt the late King, who were once taken to be his moſt loyal Subjects, and had performed him moſt acceptable Services? Nor do we in theſe very times want ſome that may boaſt of former Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices, and have been lately very dear to His Majeſty; who yet, becauſe their ambition was not anſwered, or intereſt ſerved, are fallen off, and become as deeply male-contents as others. And indeed, where men have diſcontentedly forſaken an intereſt, they are the moſt likely, as is once already obſerved, to become its worſt Enemies where opportunity ſerves, becauſe ſuch ſo engaged are moved both by intereſt and revenge. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his former Services are ſo far from taking away all belief of his Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vacy to ſuch deſigns, if any ſuch had been, that his preſent diſcontents, ſo notoriouſly diſcovered thoughout the whole Pamphlet, render him the more ſuſpitious.</p>
            <p n="3">3. He pleads Page 2. to the Reader, that he <hi>never had with his Lordſhip, viz.</hi> the E. of <hi>Sh—any other diſcourſe than was occaſional in relation to my in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended Voyage.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Which ſeems moſt improbable, becauſe he was often with his Lordſhip, and particularly with Sir <hi>Thomas Armstrong the night before his Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips Apprehenſion,</hi> Inform. Page 3. and <hi>went with his Lordſhip towards</hi> Ox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford, Page 6. Now if there was no ſuch diſcourſe as this, nor any ſuch deſign to found ſuch diſcourſe upon, can we in reaſon think, that Sir <hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas</hi> his ears muſt be entertain'd with nothing but <hi>Carolina,</hi> who was a ſtranger to that affair! So that in all his Viſits, and on the Road towards <hi>Oxford,</hi> their mouths muſt be filled with nothing but <hi>Carolina, Carolina!</hi> This cannot in any reaſon be ſuppoſed, and therefore the Captain hath made this band too ſtrait to hold. So if he means by [occaſional] any other thing that this Subject might lead them to, or to which they might paſs from this of <hi>Carolina,</hi> which might be this, or that, or any thing, then he hath profeſſed this thing to no purpoſe or advantage to himſelf.</p>
            <p>We ſhall purſue this Argument, <hi>viz.</hi> the inſufficiency of his Anſwers, to clear his innocence under the next Head, which is the Captain's Examinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, when brought by Warrant to <hi>White-hall.</hi> Which is contained in P. 8, 9.
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:51046:7"/>Where the Captain is charged as an Aſſociate in that ſuppoſed Conſpiracy, which charge was founded on ſeveral reaſons, that carryed a very fair probability that way. As</p>
            <p n="1">1. An Information upon Oath, that in this Conſpiracy the ſaid Captain was to have a Troop of Horſe, which Oath was made by Mr. <hi>Booth,</hi> who alſo depoſed that himſelf was entered a Soldier under the ſaid Captain.</p>
            <p>Now of this <hi>Booth</hi> the Captain doth own;</p>
            <p n="1">1. That he had known him above twenty years in the North of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. That he was <hi>under a very ill repute,</hi> therefore the more likely to aſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciate in an ill Deſign. And,</p>
            <p n="3">3. That notwithſtanding his ill repute, he was joyn'd with the Captain in his intended or pretended Voyage to <hi>Carolina,</hi> Page 3. Parag. 2. to the Reader. And therefore likely to have been a Companion with the Captain in this Deſign, if any ſuch had been.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Captain's offer to make a diſcovery for 2000 Guineys.</p>
            <p n="3">3. His going arm'd with the E. of <hi>Sh</hi>—who is ſince acquit; and therefore we hold him acquit, but was then under the ſame Accuſation.</p>
            <p n="4">4. To <hi>Oxford</hi> the place, where, and</p>
            <p n="5">5. Againſt the Seſſion of Parliament, the time when, this attempt was ſaid intended to have been made.</p>
            <p>Moreover it was ſworn in <hi>Colledge</hi>'s Tryal, <hi>pag.</hi> 25. That the ſaid <hi>Colledge,</hi> who ſuffered at <hi>Oxford,</hi> did ſay there were ſeveral Captains, ſome of whom he there names, with abundance more, that would be ready for this Deſign upon the King and Government, of whom about forty were there at the time the ſaid <hi>Colledge</hi> ſpake theſe things. Now from all theſe, and perhaps ſome other Cauſes and Reaſons, it might well be ſuſpected that one Captain <hi>Wil</hi>—might be in the number.</p>
            <p>To which he anſwers two things, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. I could do no leſs than wait upon him, <hi>viz.</hi> the E. of <hi>S</hi>—who had been ſo kind—<hi>pag.</hi> 6.</p>
            <p>Where obſerve that his anſwer gives a reaſon of his Attendance, but not of his Arms: Therefore it may be replied, what need was there of his going armed? no more, I ſuppoſe, than of <hi>Colledges</hi> doing ſo. His reſpects were ſhown in his perſonal attendance, not in his weapons.</p>
            <p n="2">2. He anſwers <hi>pag.</hi> 9. That he could not be ſuppoſed confederate in ſuch a deſign, if any ſuch was: for <hi>at the ſame time he,</hi> viz. <hi>Mr.</hi> Booth, <hi>ſaid this was to be, which was when the Parliament was to be last at</hi> Oxford, <hi>I had taken a Ship for</hi> Carolina.</p>
            <p>Now that Parliament was diſſolved <hi>March.</hi> 28. and at that time, ſaith he, that that Parliament was to ſit, I had taken a Ship, <hi>ergo</hi> could not be ſuppoſed to be in a deſign then at <hi>Oxford.</hi> This is a main Plea, and which he ſeems to triumph in: and yet to the Reader <hi>pag.</hi> 2. he tells you quite another ſtory, <hi>viz.</hi> that <hi>he hired this Ship in the Moneth of</hi> April: and <hi>pag.</hi> 3. adds further, that the Ship lay upon <hi>his charge from</hi> April <hi>to</hi> Auguſt: <hi>ergo</hi> was not hired till <hi>April,</hi> which was after the diſſolution of that Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and the return of all Parties to their homes.</p>
            <p>Now ſuppoſe this Ship had been hired in <hi>March,</hi> it doth not prove, but that the Captain might notwithſtanding be in a Plot at the ſame time, men may drive on a publick and private Deſign at once; and truly the proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility is ſtill the greater, ſince it is given upon Oath, that the Captain de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:51046:8"/>not to go as yet to <hi>Carolina</hi> in his own perſon, but at preſent to ſend his Son, as appears in the Hearing at the <hi>Old-Bailey.</hi> But here is a moſt ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt Contradiction, whereby he brings himſelf under a greater ſuſpicion, than if he had ſaid nothing; for that cannot be Truth, that needs a Lye.</p>
            <p>But you will ſay, Perhaps the Captain in the Preface miſtook <hi>April</hi> for <hi>March.</hi> To which I anſwer, There is no [perhaps] in the Caſe; but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trariwiſe it is very plain and certain, that in the Information he put <hi>March</hi> for <hi>April.</hi> Becauſe,</p>
            <p n="1">1. In the Information he ſaith but once that it was in <hi>March,</hi> but to the Reader he ſaith twice that it was in <hi>April.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. To the Reader, the Captain ſets himſelf to give you an account,</p>
            <p n="1">1. Of his Preparations for his Voyage, and alſo of all Particulars about the Ship, <hi>pag.</hi> 2. as the time he hired her, which was the <hi>Month of</hi> April; her Name, the <hi>Abigail of Colcheſter;</hi> her Burthen, <hi>about</hi> 130 <hi>Tuns;</hi> and the Maſter's Name, <hi>Thomas Wood.</hi> And,</p>
            <p n="2">2. Of his Loſſes in this Project, <hi>pag.</hi> 3. As particularly his having this Ship ſo long upon his charge, <hi>viz.</hi> from the Month of <hi>April</hi> till <hi>August</hi> fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing. And certainly where he ſets himſelf to give you an account of his Misfortunes and Charges, which he loves to do to all advantage, it is not in reaſon to be ſuppoſed, that he would cut off one Months Charge from the Account, which yet he muſt have done, in caſe the ſaid Ship was hired at the Seſſion of the Parliament at <hi>Oxford,</hi> which was in <hi>March.</hi> Now here he purpoſely gives you an account of all the little Circumſtances about the Ship, and the loſſes he ſuſtain'd: Therefore there being no other Matter at that inſtant before him, here was a free recollection of his thoughts, and therefore no danger of a miſtake in ſo plain and eaſie a Matter; and yet in each place he ſaith, <hi>April</hi> was the time he hired the Ship, and the time her Charges took date upon him. Whereas in the Information there was very complex Matter before him, and he ſpoke of <hi>March</hi> incidently, and <hi>in tranſitu,</hi> to ſome other Matter, therefore might more eaſily miſtake than in the other; if you will be ſo merciful as to ſuppoſe a miſtake, which you cannot do without the forfeiture of your Reaſon. Becauſe,</p>
            <p n="3">3. To the Reader, he could have no deſign in naming the circumſtance of Time; whereas in the Information he had a very great one, in ſaying it was in <hi>March;</hi> for hereby he would wipe off all Suſpicions of his being in a Plot then.</p>
            <p>Whence it is ten thouſand times more likely that he ſhould falſifie in the Information, than miſtake to the Reader; and conſequently in all reaſon the former Account was true, <hi>viz.</hi> that the Ship was hired in <hi>April,</hi> after all was over, and poſſibly to carry him off from danger. I would not judg the Captain, but truly this Shift hath a wicked Aſpect, and ſuch an evil In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence on the repute of his Loyalty, that it will not eaſily be recovered.</p>
            <p>Now after all this, who can wonder that there was expectation above of ſome great Diſcovery; that his Examination was ſo ſtrict and preſſing; and that my <hi>Lord Chancellor</hi> was ſo cloſe upon him; when beſide Oath made againſt him, even himſelf had given ſo juſt an occaſion of ſuch ſtrictneſs in the ſeveral Particulars before mentioned, and now at laſt by putting off the Charge from himſelf by a very Lye? Had the Captain been in ſome Places, far leſs occaſion would have brought him to Examination by Rack or Lim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bo; therefore he might well be content, as he is pleaſed to word it, <hi>pag.</hi> 8.
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:51046:8"/>
               <hi>to run the Gantlet from one Place to another.</hi> We ſee many times that in a Cauſe of ſo narrow a Sphere, as not to reach any farther than a private Concern, Witneſſes are examin'd, croſs-examin'd, and run this, that, and every way, by cloſe and ſubtil Queries; are now affrighted, and then dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dled in their own humours, and Matters applied in the moſt likely way to ſift truth out of them; that I have ſeen the man ſweat, and almoſt at his wits end; and having ſpoke truth at firſt, though others were not well ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied he did ſo, hath as much cauſe to ſuſpect and complain that the Court would have frighted, or perſwaded him to Perjury, as the Captain hath to reflect all that diſhonour upon theſe Perſonages, whoſe Parts and Integrity are, under his Majeſty, the Glory of our Court and Age, the Security of our Peace, Properties and Religion, and who therefore are honoured by good men, feared and hated by the evil, and admired by all.</p>
            <p>And truly ſometimes Truth is not diſcoverable without diligent Search, ſtrict and various Methods, and repeated Examinations: Therefore <hi>Fitz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>harris,</hi> and many others of the <hi>Popiſh</hi> way, had very frequent Examinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, Promiſes, Threatnings, and all imaginable Methods practiſed to draw truth from them. Yet theſe People will not endure any Suſpicions of ſuch De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns from them, who are ſaid thus to examine others themſelves, as the Captain would perſwade were by like means upon himſelf. Sound places will not mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſuch rubbing, when ſore parts ſhrink from the hand that touches them.</p>
            <p>Well, we have here ſome of the moſt ſatisfactory Evidences, both of the vanity of mens Minds, and the corruption of their Manners; and that par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly in their having eſpouſed a Cauſe and a Party, and their being re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved right or wrong, or however that Party act in all the ways of wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, yet ſtill to hold on that ſide, and bring all the Fig-leaves they can, to cover its ſhame and nakedneſs. That</p>
            <p n="1">1. They ſo readily receive the Information of an indigent caſt Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, who ſtands corrupt in his Principles, and whoſe Loyalty is turned to revenge; or any other wretched Pamphlet ſtuffed full with Lyes, and moſt palpable contradictions, and all this againſt the King and chief Miniſters of State; againſt the Government and Juſtice of the Nation: Notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding theſe very Practices of <hi>blackning the King, viz.</hi> in his Perſon, Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters and Government, was the beginner and inlet of that Rebellion, which coſt ſo many thouſand Lives, and hath brought ſo much reproach upon all Religion. And that it is the daily buſineſs of ſeparate Congregations by the ſame cauſe to produce the ſame effect. The plainneſs of ſuch De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns and Practices, ſhould make all honeſt men, that are not willing to encourage, and therefore partake in thoſe moſt damning ſins of Rebellion, Murthers, Theft, and all manner of Villanies that Rebellion leads to, not to judge their Judges, not <hi>to revile the Gods,</hi> not to receive an Accuſation, or <hi>true Proteſtant Stories</hi> and <hi>Intelligences,</hi> becauſe it is from that foul cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, that all vile Accuſations, fulſom Reports, black Repreſentations of all preſent Eſtabliſhments, and every Accuſation <hi>of the Brethren, which is the work of the Devil, doth come.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſhall give you only one inſtance of the falſhood of theſe Intelligences, and that is in <hi>Langly Curtis,</hi> who ſaith, <hi>Numb.</hi> 93. that the Aſſociation which is printed by His Majeſties Command in the Lord <hi>Sh</hi>—Hearing at the <hi>Old-Baily,</hi> is only an Aſſociation for the Preſervation of the King and Proteſtant Religion, and was propoſed in the Houſe of Commons. We will conſider the thing in ſome Particulars: As</p>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:51046:9"/>
            <p>It ingages for the defence of the King, but how?</p>
            <p n="1">1. By Diſbanding his Forces. And</p>
            <p n="2">2. By excluding the King, the Lords, and thoſe Commons that will not aſſociate from the Government, or to follow the aſſociating Party exclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive of the reſt, which is directly to ſet up another <hi>Rump-Parliament.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. It directly ſets up Arbitrary Power and Government. For</p>
            <p n="1">1. It ingages to follow the Orders of the aſſociating Lords and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, while they Sit, when prorogued, or after Diſſolution; whatever thoſe Orders be, or however contrary to all Fundamental Laws of the Land. And</p>
            <p n="2">2. To <hi>purſue to destruction all</hi> that oppoſe it, which the King and every honeſt Subject muſt do.</p>
            <p n="3">3. For the effecting all which, they ingage to obey the Orders and Officers which this ſuppoſed Rump of a Parliament ſhall ſet over them, in the ſeveral Countries, Cities, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>— all which is to be done while the King lives, for it adds, <hi>if any fail in the Proſecution hereof, viz,</hi> of the Aſſociati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>they ſhall be—proſecuted, and ſuppreſt—as Enemies to God, the King, &amp;c. Ergo,</hi> this muſt be put in Execution while the King doth live.</p>
            <p>Therefore this is juſt ſuch a defence of the King, as the late Rebellion, which pretended His Majeſties Honour and Safety; but we ſee in the end, that men fought for King and Parliament, till they brought the King to Deſtruction, as this Aſſociation ingages to do.</p>
            <p>And yet, ſaith <hi>Langly Curtis,</hi> this was propoſed in the late Parliament, I hope the next Parliament will give him no thanks for reporting them to aſſociate in a Rebellion, and conſult matters of High-Treaſon, as the thruſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the King from the Government, and bringing His Majeſty, and all Loyal Subjects to deſtruction, under the notion of Popiſh Adherents, and Oppoſers of this Aſſociation. Whether this doth not tend to the faſtning ſome Reports upon the Houſe, let any judge.</p>
            <p>Therefore I preſume, that as the Lord <hi>Shaftsbury</hi> doth not approve theſe things, ſo the Houſe will prove the <hi>True Proteſtant</hi> to be a <hi>Lying Mercury.</hi> Theſe are Religious Wheedles, made to reconcile ignorant minds to the blackeſt Villanies, and to throw <hi>Samuel</hi>'s Mantle over the Devil of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion.</p>
            <p>A man ſhould not be more careful of his Pocket when a Cheat is at his Elbow, than he ſhould of his Ear, when a <hi>true Protestant</hi> whiſper ſalutes it, or a Libel approaches. A doing ſo would argue an honeſt wary mind, that ſtands upon its watch againſt the ſly Inſinuations and Devices of the evil one. Whereas a receiving ſuch, becauſe <hi>true Protestant Stories,</hi> that is in plain Engliſh, <hi>Religious Lyes,</hi> is the giving up your ſelves to Deluſions, and a Reprobate ſenſe.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That men will believe the ſurmiſes, whiſpers, and inventions of a Jeſuited Proteſtant, rather than what all men ſee, and know, <hi>viz.</hi> the moſt can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>did proceedings of Authority, and equal adminiſtration of Laws without partiality, unleſs it be on their own ſide, and by their own means. Such are our Governours, ſuch are our Circumſtances, that any Nation in the World (was it not for the miſchiefs our ſelves do make) would ſay of us, <hi>Happy are the people that are in ſuch a caſe!</hi> For we have ſuch a ſettled Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, that no reformed Church in the world will offer to condemn: Such ſecurity of our Perſons and Eſtates, that nothing can be greater:
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:51046:9"/>ſuch increaſe of Shipping, Merchants, and Trade, that we ſhame, not only Complaints, and <hi>Petitions,</hi> that would be faſtning ſome fault upon the the Government, but even all. Ages before us. We have no fears, but what are either of our own making, or at a diſtance from us, which the happieſt and beſt governed Society in the World is expoſed to. What greater Argument is there of a reprobate mind, a mind abandoned to all folly and miſchief that can complain in ſuch a Golden Age! That can wiſh to run out of Gods Bleſſing into the warm Sun! from ſuch an happy State, and Government into Confuſion, Plunders, Oppreſſions, and Arbitrary Government; and all this out of hopes of a fine <hi>Chimaera</hi> of our own ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king! This is exactly to play the part of a wilful <hi>Iſrael,</hi> who would have left <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron,</hi> and have made themſelves Captains of their own, and have returned to their Fleſh-pots in <hi>Egypt!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What greater Argument that God hath given up men to be their own ſhame and Executioners, than this, that they are ſo willing to follow thoſe men, who by lies, perjuries, and every evil method, have deſtroyed the Government, and themſelves once already; and are again taking the ſame meaſures, and think nothing unlawful that ſerves to the ſame end. Was there not a lying Spirit gone forth into the mouths of the Prophets to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade this People to go up, and fall at <hi>Ramoth-Gilead?</hi> Was it not the Souls of a Martyred Soveraign, and of loyal Subjects murthered in his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, that cries under the Altar, for vengeance upon them? Was it not from a Decree of Heaven, that all the righteous blood ſhed amongſt us ſhould come upon this Generation; certainly ſuch folly and wickedneſs could never be.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That no Information can be received againſt one that is a <hi>True Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testant,</hi> as Proteſtant Recuſants call themſelves, while any Charge ſhall ſtand good againſt another: That the ſame Witneſſes are in one caſe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſtionable, but in another muſt neceſſarily be perjured Rogues and Villains! On the one hand, every thing is huff'd off with a <hi>Sham:</hi> on the other, every whining Story and Conventicle Lye is judg'd infallible, as if it was impoſſible for Truth to be on this ſide, or Falſhood on that: and becauſe men judge before they know the cauſe, they are, however the cenſure fall, but unjuſt Judges.</p>
            <p>To believe a <hi>Fitz-harris,</hi> when all hopes of life were taken from him, and therefore no room left for the World to offer him a Temptation is hereſy and damnation: but not to believe a Captain <hi>Wilkinſon</hi> on his bare and eaſie word, when he was poor and likely to live to enjoy the rewards of ſin, is ſo too!</p>
            <p>Now that <hi>Fitz-harris</hi> ſhould falſify for nothing, and that in ſo high a nature, and at his death too; or if in hope he had done ſo, yet that ſo great a ſervice ſhould receive no reward, neither in his Perſon nor Family, is the wonder of reaſon. But that the Captain might falſify, who was an hopeleſs Priſoner, ſet a price on his own ſervices, and upon his Informati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, is diſcharged of his Debts, releaſed from a Priſon, and keeps his Lodg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings in Town, is a thing very ſuſpicious. Yet to believe the former in any thing, or not to believe the latter in all things, is the greateſt Villany in the world.</p>
            <p>And while you object what you pleaſe againſt <hi>Fitz-harris,</hi> I pray withal conſider how credible a Perſon the Captain is: And that you may ſee him in his Colours, I ſhall repeat ſome things, together with a few new Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marks on his Information. As,</p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:51046:10"/>
            <p n="1">1. In the Preface he tells you, That had he had the liberty others did enjoy, he would have made his Information known to his Majeſty, before he had publiſhed it to the World; where he makes the Reaſon to be want of Power, not of Will; which is ſo notoriouſly falſe, that it can admit of no Palliation: For by his own Story, he knew all the Deſign upon him, before he was brought to <hi>Whitehall,</hi> where he might have diſcovered the Matter to his Majeſty, who was pleaſed to ſee him, had he been ſo minded. Indeed his Information was not then writ; perhaps he had not yet adviſed upon it, or wanted ſome Notes from his <hi>ſober</hi> and <hi>ſenſible</hi> Friend: But had this been all, no man doubts, but that he might have ſent his Information to Court, or in that Juncture, might have had the liberty of going himſelf, had he deſired it. This is ſo bald a pretence, that, like a Winter Cuckow, it hath no Feathers to hide its Scabs and Nakedneſs.</p>
            <p n="2">2. To the Reader, <hi>pag.</hi> 1. he tells you, His Majeſties Service did impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veriſh him; and yet <hi>parag.</hi> 2. and 8. he takes a great deal of pains to prove himſelf a Lyar: And that by ſhowing he had undone himſelf by many foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh Projects, by fond Engagements for other men, by ſpending above one thouſand pounds upon his Friend, and by keeping a Ship, Family, and above thirty Servants, ſeveral months idle on the River, and by Suits, which Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſengers brought upon him, by being all that time hindered by him in their Voyages.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Information, <hi>pag.</hi> 2. he ſaith, That <hi>Octob.</hi> 11. he might have had 500 <hi> l. per an.</hi> to himſelf and Heirs, or 10000 <hi>l.</hi> in money, for diſcovering what he knew;—and yet <hi>pag.</hi> 3, and 4. he confeſſes, that the next day he did himſelf offer to diſcover for 2000 Guineys; which low Demands this day give the Lye to his pretended Offers the day before.</p>
            <p n="4">4. In all his Examination, and the heavy Charge he complains of at Court, before his Majeſty, <hi>Lord Chancellor,</hi> Lord <hi>Hallifax,</hi> Lord <hi>Hyde,</hi> the two Secretaries, and <hi>Lord Chief Justice—pag.</hi> 8. Mr. <hi>Booth</hi> and Mr. <hi>Bains</hi> preſent; though he found his Examination the ſtricter, becauſe of his own Talk and Offers, yet he never told any why he had made ſuch Offers, or that any Endeavours were uſed to corrupt him; which certainly any man would have done, had any ſuch thing been; eſpecially the Captain, who in the Preface pretends an inclination and willingneſs to have made the Matter of his Information known to his Majeſty. The Deſign, it ſeems, was not yet ripe, nor the Beaſt licked into the ſhape, it now appears, and affrights the World in.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Mr. <hi>Booth</hi> doth charge him to his face, that he was once again to ride Captain, <hi>pag.</hi> 9. but the Captain doth not tax the ſaid <hi>Booth</hi> with this Vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lany, which, if true, and then made known, might have brought himſelf off with the more eaſe and credit; therefore he muſt have a large Swal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, that can let ſuch a Gudgeon down. If any can perſwade me that an honeſt man ſhall be aſſaulted by a Thief, and by the ſame Thief ſhall be brought before a Magiſtrate, and there be charged with capital Crimes, and yet all this while that this honeſt man ſhall not diſcover to the Magiſtrate the others Rogueries, then I will believe the Captain's Story.</p>
            <p n="6">6. He tells you, to the Reader, twice over, that he hired the Ship in <hi>April;</hi> and yet Infor. <hi>pag.</hi> 9. to help himſelf at a dead lift, he ſaith, he hired her in <hi>March.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Truly the man is a meer <hi>Hocus pocus,</hi> an <hi>Hiccius, doctius;</hi> he is here, and there, and every where, and yet no where at all. For,</p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:51046:10"/>
            <p n="7">7. He tells you, <hi>pag.</hi> 4. that he knows ſomething, and yet knows no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing; that he will diſcover, and yet hath nothing to diſcover; and yet ſtill asks a great deal of money for diſcovery of what he knows.</p>
            <p n="8">8. He adds, <hi>pag.</hi> 9. That when he was about ready for his <hi>Voyage, he was like a man bewitched, and could neither budge nor ſtir,—that my ſelf and Wife concluded there was a divine Hand in it.</hi> So that here a kind of Witch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ery, or a divine Hand, neither himſelf nor learned Wife could tell whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, but ſome unaccountable Cauſe it muſt be that hindered him. Which indeed takes mainly with the Rabble, who mightily gaze after Signs in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, or on the Earth; and hence conclude, that this is a Gentleman de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign'd by Providence to be a kind of Saviour to them. But yet to the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, <hi>pag.</hi> 3. he tells you, That Mr. <hi>Booth,</hi> and <hi>other Freightors failing, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with ſome Difficulties which I met with,—hindered him.</hi> Before it was either Witchery, or a divine Hand, a ſtrange Amuſe and Confuſion; but here it was no ſuch matter, but Paſſengers, and other Buſineſs, that hindered. Whence truly I am eaſily perſwaded he was at leaſt <hi>like one be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>witched,</hi> if not really ſo, elſe he had never troubled the World with ſuch a pack of Non-ſence and Contradictions.</p>
            <p>Now this is your <hi>True-man,</hi> a <hi>true Proteſtant,</hi> I warrant you; one that can no more tell a Lye, than <hi>Fitz-harris</hi> can Truth.</p>
            <p>But I do not ſo much preſs the reception of his Declaration, nor the reje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the other's Information, as ſhow from hence the giddy Humours, the byaſs'd Affections, and unequal Cenſures of men, who meaſure all good and evil, Truth and Falſhood, by this and t'other Side or Party; that no dram of Truth and Honeſty can be allow'd on one ſide, nor any ſcruple of Knavery on the other. Men are now perfect Saints or perfect Devils, and muſt be ſaved or damn'd according to the Side they ſpeak for. Now all Religion conſiſts in being of a Party, and they are <hi>Names, not Crimes, that hang or ſave. Paſſion and Interest hath ſwallowed up all Honesty and Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; and good Nature is overborn by wicked Reſolutions.</hi> We are fallen into an Age of Miracles, but ſuch as <hi>Moſes</hi> and the Prophets, ſuch as Chriſt and his Apoſtles, or any Apoſtolick man, never wrought. For now the Hand alters the nature of the Action: Rebellion and Murther is ſuch in a <hi>Papiſt</hi>-Subject, but in a true <hi>Proteſtant</hi> they are Arguments of Grace. The ſin of butchering Kings lyes not in the Act, but in the manner of Execution, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be by Sword, Piſtol, Poyſon, which are <hi>Popiſh</hi> things, or by a <hi>true Protestant-Hatchet,</hi> which is the <hi>Honour</hi> and Priviledge <hi>of the Saints.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But you will ſay the Captain proves all by two little Informations an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>next to his own; the one by <hi>Jarvis James,</hi> the other by his Wife.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Jarvis James,</hi> how ſtands he qualified for an Evidence?</p>
            <p>Why thus.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Jarvis James, Gent.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Jarvis James, fellow-Priſoner with the Captain.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Jarvis James,</hi> One of the good People, as it is ſaid, that carried on the <hi>Work of the Lord against the Lord's Anointed:</hi> Birds of a feather flock together; if you may gueſs a man by his Familiar, you may ſee which Side the Captain ſtands on.</p>
            <p n="4">4. He is a very <hi>ſenſible Perſon.</hi> Whether doth he mean, ſenſible of his own former Miſcarriages, or of the Captain's preſent Knavery, or both? But however you underſtand it, what doth this Gentleman ſay? Why even all this, <hi>viz.</hi> that he had the Captain's Information by piece-meal from
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:51046:11"/>his own mouth. Very good; but wherein the Captain might prevaricate, this <hi>ſenſible Gentleman</hi> cannot tell, but muſt paſs with an <hi>Ignoramus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Here is the Captain's Wife turn'd Informer, who comes with Twins in her Womb: She brings forth her firſt-born on <hi>Wedneſday, Octob.</hi> 12. and her ſecond on <hi>Friday, Octob.</hi> 14. and both in the ſame year. Certainly if the Captain's Wife be ſo fruitful, the King will never want Souldiers. But what is it the Woman ſaith? Not that Mr. <hi>Booth</hi> preſſed her Husband to Perjury, but to witneſs—that is, to ſwear what things it was ſuppoſed he might be privy to. A main Matter truly, and no more than what others have done in other Caſes, without any Slanders caſt upon them; but in the Good Old Cauſe every Gooſe muſt be a Swan:
<q>Parturiunt montes, neſcetur ridiculus mus!</q> But you will ſay, Her Husband was promiſed Rewards to ſwear; and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps now others will ſay, He hath ſaved his pains, and got his Rewards too. Truly I do not know one <hi>Popiſh</hi> Evidence but what had his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, and ſome of them Promiſes antecedent, and as inducements to a Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery: And ſince the Captain was poor and covetous, and declares him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf an Enemy to the Court for want of Rewards, I do not underſtand the evil of making ſome ſhows of Rewards by way of Search and Experiment, whether his Prejudices were removable, and the man capable of being brought to himſelf, and Truth together. We ſee that both <hi>He</hi> and <hi>She</hi>-Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence can follow the way of <hi>Balaam:</hi> There is a Lip-adultery, and a Miſs can be kept for the ſervice of her Tongue, as well as of other Parts. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore whether the Captain knew any thing really, or in pretence only, yet if he lay to make an advantage, and was looking after the Calves of <hi>Bethel,</hi> whether it might not be both prudent and honeſt to make ſhow of ſome bait, to ſtay him till he had time to conſider matter of duty, as well as intereſt only, I leave any that are no paries as being concerned in the Cauſe, to judg. But that it is very unreaſonable to believe there were any rewards propoſed, appears,</p>
            <p n="1">1. From the particulars urged in that behalf.</p>
            <p n="2">2. From the Captains many falſifications, and incongruities, which ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the whole obnoxious to the juſt ſuſpicions of a vile impoſture.</p>
            <p n="3">3. From the want of proof; for it is unreaſonable to take up a report, eſpecially in weighty concerns, as theſe are, without ſufficient warrant for ſo doing; but here is no warrant at all: for as <hi>Booth</hi> and <hi>Bains</hi> are par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties on the one hand, who deny it; ſo the Captain and his Wife, who affirm it, are parties on the other hand. For in any cauſe gain doth make any perſons parties; and now whether the Captain and his Wife were not gainers in this matter, I leave to the reaſons of any men to judg from the ſole conſideration of their immediate releaſe hereupon from priſon, and advance to the ſtate of a Gentleman.</p>
            <p n="4">4. A Wife is a good Witneſs againſt an Husband, becauſe in ſuch a caſe ſhe ſpeaks againſt her ſelf; but her teſtimony is not ſo valid for him, by reaſon his Cauſe and Intereſt is her own; this is therefore but little better than to ask my fellow if I am a thief; to try an High-way man by his own Gang, or any Priſoner by them of his own way. But in the moſt divided intereſt ſhe is but one, and I hope an <hi>Ignoramus</hi> may as well paſs againſt a ſingle teſtimony, as againſt eight; eſpecially if the <hi>good men and true</hi> come fore-arm'd with a reſolution not to believe the Evidence.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:51046:11"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
